<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>SUD Guidelines on SUD</title>
    <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/</link>
    <description>Recent content in SUD Guidelines on SUD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>@agent</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/deep_features/agent/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/deep_features/agent/</guid>
      <description>The @agent feature is used for arguments that are agents of their governor at the semantic level in various constructions (e.g., causative, passive, impersonal, etc.).
    </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>@caus</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/deep_features/caus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/deep_features/caus/</guid>
      <description>The @caus feature is used for the argument of causative auxiliaries.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>@expl</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/deep_features/expletive/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/deep_features/expletive/</guid>
      <description>The @expl feature is used for arguments of predicates without semantic contents (impersonal subjects for instance).   This feature can also be used to annotate repeated subjects, such as those which are common in certain French interrogative constructions.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>@fixed (DEPRECATED)</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/deep_features/fixed/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/deep_features/fixed/</guid>
      <description>The @fixed feature was previously used for multi-word expression. It has been replaced by nodes features: see here</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>@lvc</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/deep_features/lvc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/deep_features/lvc/</guid>
      <description>The @lvc feature is used for arguments of light verbs.
 English
   French
  See issue #5 for a discussion about light verb construction annotation in SUD.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>@pass</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/deep_features/pass/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/deep_features/pass/</guid>
      <description>The @pass feature is used for the arguments of passive auxiliaries.
The relation between the auxiliary and the verb is marked comp:aux@pass and the subject of the auxiliary bears the subj@pass feature.
 English
   French
  In case of passive reflexive constructions, the subject is analysed with a regular subj relation and the pronoun with the comp@pass relation. For more information about the usage of comp, see the dedicated page.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>@relcl</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/deep_features/relcl/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/deep_features/relcl/</guid>
      <description>The @relcl feature is used for the relation between the head of a relative clause and its antecedent.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>@tense</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/deep_features/tense/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/deep_features/tense/</guid>
      <description>The @tense feature is used for the argument of tense auxiliaries.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>@x</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/deep_features/x/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/deep_features/x/</guid>
      <description>The @x feature is used to annotate relationships with verbs that do not have an explicitly marked subject, but whose semantic subject can nevertheless be found in the sentence. This relationship therefore applies essentially to infinitive verbs which relate to a subject introduced earlier in the sentence. For example, in the sentence he wants to eat, he has a clear semantic relationship with to eat.
  While this feature is most often used in relationships between finite verbs and the infinitives they govern, note that the governing element does not necessarily need to be a verb.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>comp</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/relations/comp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/relations/comp/</guid>
      <description>The comp relation is used for arguments of verbs, nouns, adjectives, adverbs, auxiliaries, adpositions and conjunctions.
This relation is refined into several sub-relations: comp:aux (auxiliary argument), comp:cleft (cleft clauses), comp:obj (direct object),comp:obl (oblique argument), comp:pred (predicative argument).
In most cases, SUD native corpora are directly annotated with the sub-relations, rather than with the comp relation. However, comp may sometimes be used when one has difficulty deciding between comp:obj and comp:obl.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>comp:aux</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/relations/comp_aux/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/relations/comp_aux/</guid>
      <description>The comp:aux relation is used for the argument of auxiliaries, and corresponds to the aux relationship as defined by UD.
 English
   English
  Multiple auxiliaries, such as those permitted in English varieties spoken in the Southeastern United States, are annotated as so.
 Southern American English
   Naija
   Slovak
   Wolof
   German
  Deep syntactic features The relation comp:aux can have these features:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>comp:cleft</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/relations/comp_cleft/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/relations/comp_cleft/</guid>
      <description>The comp:cleft relation is used in cleft sentences for the dependency from the head of the sentence to the head of the complement clause.
 English
   French
  Sometimes, there is an ambiguity between a relative clause and a cleft clause. Consider the sentence It is the electric car that I chose.
If someone utters this sentence in a context where they must choose between a gasoline car and an electric car, the sentence is interpreted as a cleft sentence with the following annotation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>comp:obj</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/relations/comp_obj/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/relations/comp_obj/</guid>
      <description>The comp:obj relation is used for direct object complements, including direct complements of an adposition or a subordinating conjunction.
Direct object complements  English
   French
   Russian
  Usually, in order to determine whether an object is direct or not, it suffices to know if it forms a construction with a preposition. If it doesn&amp;rsquo;t, the object is direct. According to different languages, this criterion may be insufficient.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>comp:obl</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/relations/comp_obl/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/relations/comp_obl/</guid>
      <description>The comp:obl relation is used for oblique arguments of verbs, adjectives, adverbs, nouns or pronouns, regardless of their form. Unlike UD, SUD does not make a distinction between indirect objects and oblique arguments. SUD instead makes the distinction between arguments and modifiers.
Consider the following sentence analyzed in UD.
 English
  In SUD, it would be analyzed as follows:
 English
  Oblique complement of a verb  English</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>comp:pred</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/relations/comp_pred/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/relations/comp_pred/</guid>
      <description>The comp:pred relation is used for predicative arguments of verbs.
 English
   English
   English
   English
   French
   French
  The comp:pred relation can also be used in certain subordinating constructions.
 French
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparative, superlative and consecutive constructions</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/particular_phenomena/comparative/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/particular_phenomena/comparative/</guid>
      <description>In comparative constructions where each term is introduced with a grammatical pair like more&amp;hellip; than, the relation between the two grammatical words is labeled comp:obj, with the first word being the head of the second. Consider the example:
 French
  Note that the first grammatical word of the comparison (plus) is considered a modifier of the property being compared. Examples in other languages: plus &amp;hellip; que (French), più &amp;hellip; di (Italian), bardziej &amp;hellip; niż (Polish).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Compound</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/particular_phenomena/compounds/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/particular_phenomena/compounds/</guid>
      <description>SUD shares with with UD its compound relation, though the exact usage of this relationship is determined on a language-by-language basis. SUD annotations for some languages, such as French, do not use the compound relation at all.
Naija in particular makes heavy use of this relation, which is used to link nouns to virtually any other nouns which play a modifying role. However, it is also used to annotate phrasal verbs as well as a more limited subset of relations between nouns and adjectives, such as dry cleaner, which are considered fixed expressions whose meaning cannot be directly understood from its constituent parts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>conj:appos</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/conj_appos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/conj_appos/</guid>
      <description>This relation is used for appositions. In an apposition, conjuncts have the same referent, but two clearly different denotations. The conjunct in apposition forms a predication in the background (in Mary, my best friend, the second conjunct my best friend is a predication on the first conjunct Mary, it is equivalent to Mary is my best friend).
Ex:
 French
   Naija
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>conj:coord</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/conj_coord/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/conj_coord/</guid>
      <description>This relation is used to link elements connected with a coordinating conjunction such as and and or. The conjunction itself is linked to the second element with a cc relation. It is analogous to conj relation in UD and SUD for written language.
 French
   Naija
  In case of multiple coordinating constructions, we analyze them in a chain in contrast to UD, which analyzes them as a bouquet structure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>conj:dicto</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/conj_dicto/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/conj_dicto/</guid>
      <description>This relation is used to indicate difluencies when a speaker corrects his speech and to analyse reformulations. The relation conj:coord is used to link two different objects, two referants (ex: Mary and John are two different referents). The relation conj:dicto on the other hand is used to link two denotations of the same referent (ex: the desert in Kenya, the Kenya desert is denoting the same referant).
The ability of conj:dicto to anlyse both disfluencies and reformulations is the reason why we don&amp;rsquo;t use the the reparandum relationship as used in UD.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coordination</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/particular_phenomena/coord/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/particular_phenomena/coord/</guid>
      <description>Chained conjuncts In UD, all conjuncts of a coordination are attached to the head of the first conjunct in a bouquet. In SUD, each conjunct is attached to the head of the previous one in a chain.
The first example below shows the annotation of a coordination in UD and the second one the corresponding annotation in SUD.
 English
   English
  Embedded coordination The conjunct of a coordination can itself be a coordination.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>discourse</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/discourse/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/discourse/</guid>
      <description>The discourse relation is used to link discourse markers. These markers are not clearly linked to the structure of the sentence, except in an expressive way.
In some cases the discourse marker can be another proposition. Ex: He comes on wednesday, I think. In this sentence I think is a discourse marker because it lacks an object (the object of the verb think is the rest of the sentence) and because they are fixed (I think doesn&amp;rsquo;t commute with he thinks).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disfluencies in oral language</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/disfulencies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/disfulencies/</guid>
      <description>In oral language, speakers form sentences while speaking, which means that sometimes they might search for words while speaking. They may repeat a word until they find the right one, or they may try with one word and then decide to change.
Repetitions and reformulations To analyse constructions of repetition or reformulation, we use the relation conj:dicto.
 French
  The conj:dicto relation applies also when the linked words are not the same.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>dislocated</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/dislocated/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/dislocated/</guid>
      <description>The dislocated relation is used to analyze detached elements that do not enter in the core grammatical relations of a sentence.
 French
   Naija
  This relation can also be used for pronouns which are detached from the core syntactic structure of an utterance, such as French tonic pronouns.
 French
   Naija
  In case of multiple propositions in one sentence, dislocated is used when the second proposition doesn&amp;rsquo;t hold any actual information value and it cannot be neither separated nor negated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Light verb constructions</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/particular_phenomena/lvc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/particular_phenomena/lvc/</guid>
      <description>A light verb construction (LVC) is a type of verbal structure in which a verb is coupled with another element – typically a noun phrase – which provides the primary semantic value. Common examples of LVCs in English include take a walk, give a kiss, or have a drink. In SUD, LVCs are marked with the deep feature @lvc.
 French
  The complements of these constructions are sometimes attached to the noun rather than the verb because:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Macrosyntactic relations</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/macrosyntax/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/macrosyntax/</guid>
      <description>In this part we will present relations that we use to analyse relations beyond the microsyntactic analysis between a governor and its dependant. We call this type of analysis macrosyntax.
This approach can be used to analyse two elements that are placed side by side with no explicit marker of coordination, subordination, or argument relation with the head word. Ex: I told him don&amp;rsquo;t do it. in this sentence we miss the usual marker that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>mod</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/relations/mod/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/relations/mod/</guid>
      <description>The modrelation is used for modifiers of verbs, nouns, adjectives, adverbs, auxiliaries, adpositions and conjunctions.
 English
   English
   French
  Deep syntactic features The relation mod can have these features:
 @relcl @x  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paradigmatical lists</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/conj/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/conj/</guid>
      <description>In UD there are three relations reparandum, conj, appos that SUD only uses for analysing written texts.
These three relations work as paradigmatic lists. That&amp;rsquo;s why in SUD for oral speech, we decided to gather these three relations under the relation conj to underline the similarity between the three.
We distinguish:
 conj:dicto for disfluencies when the speaker corrects his speech (parallel to reparandum in written texts) conj:coord for elements connected by a coordinating conjunction (parallel to conj in written texts) conj:appos for appositional modifiers that serve to define better the previous noun (parallel to appos in written texts)  Note : for analysing oral speech we never use the conj relationship alone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>parataxis:insert</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/parataxis_insert/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/parataxis_insert/</guid>
      <description>The parataxis:insert is used for inserted clause. Contrary to a parenthetical clause, an inserted clause could not form an independent sentence
 French
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>parataxis:obj</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/parataxis_obj/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/parataxis_obj/</guid>
      <description>The depency relation parataxis:obj has been deleted.
Direct discourse is attached its governor by the relation comp:obj with the features Reported = &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo;.
 French
   Naija
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>parataxis:parenth</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/parataxis_parenth/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/parataxis_parenth/</guid>
      <description>The parataxis:parenth relation is used for parenthetical clauses, in the sense that the clause is backgrounded (as if it were inside parentheses). A parenthetical clause could form an independent sentence.
 French
   Naija
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>subj</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/relations/subj/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/relations/subj/</guid>
      <description>The subj relation is used for all subjects, regardless of their form (nominal or verbal). This relationship encompasses both the nsubj and csubj relationships as defined by UD, as the following examples show.
 English
   English
  Deep syntactic features The subj relation has two deep syntactic sub-relations. The sub-relation subj@expl is used to indicate that the subject is present to fill in an obligatory syntactic position and has no semantic value.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>udep</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/relations/udep/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/relations/udep/</guid>
      <description>The udep relation is used for complements when one does not wish to or is unable to distinguish between arguments and modifiers. This relationship can notably be used in cases where the complement&amp;rsquo;s relationship with its governor is ambiguous. When there is little debate about the nature of the relationship, the more specific label is preferred.
The governor and the dependent of a udep relation can have any POS. The udep relation is frequently given to the complements of nouns, since it is generally more difficult to distinguish between arguments and modifiers for nouns than it is for verbs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>vocative</title>
      <link>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/vocative/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://surfacesyntacticud.github.io/guidelines/u/oral_language/vocative/</guid>
      <description>The vocative relation is used when a speaker directly addresses a listener in an utterance.
 French
   Naija
  </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
